Comms Market Dynamic Device Personalization (DDP) Package
======================================================================
May 12, 2022


Contents
========
- Overview
- Supported Operating Systems
- Safe Mode
- Notes
- Installation
- Troubleshooting
- Legal


Overview
========
Devices based on the Intel(R) Ethernet 800 Series require a Dynamic Device
Personalization (DDP) package file to enable advanced features (such as dynamic
tunneling, Intel(R) Ethernet Flow Director, RSS, and ADQ).

DDP allows you to change the packet processing pipeline of a device by applying
a profile package to the device at runtime. Profiles can be used to, for
example, add support for new protocols, change existing protocols, or change
default settings. DDP profiles can also be rolled back without rebooting the
system.

The DDP package loads during device initialization or driver runtime, depending
on the operating system. The driver checks to see if the DDP package is present
and compatible. If this file exists, the driver will load it into the device.
If the DDP package file is missing or incompatible with the driver, the driver
will go into Safe Mode where it will use the configuration contained in the
device's NVM. Refer to the Intel(R) Ethernet Adapters and Devices User Guide
for more information on Safe Mode.

A general-purpose, default DDP package is automatically installed with all
supported Intel Ethernet 800 Series drivers on supported operating systems.
Additional DDP packages are available to address needs for specific market
segments or targeted solutions.

The default DDP package supports the following:
- MAC
- EtherType
- VLAN
- IPv4
- IPv6
- TCP
- ARP
- UDP
- SCTP
- ICMP
- ICMPv6
- CTRL
- LLDP
- VXLAN-GPE
- VXLAN (non-GPE)
- Geneve
- GRE
- NVGRE
- RoCEv2
- MPLS (up to 5 consecutive MPLS labels in the outermost Layer 2 header group)

In addition to the previous list, the Comms Market DDP package also supports
the following:
- GTPv1 and GTPv2 with extension headers
- PPPOE
- L2TPv3
- IPSec
- PFCP


Supported Operating Systems
===========================
This DDP package is supported on the following operating systems:
- Linux*
- VMware* ESXi*

NOTE: ESXi support for DDP packages for specific market segments requires the
following:
- OS: ESXi 6.7 or higher
- Driver: icen 1.9.1.x or higher
- Tool: intnet 1.8.3.x or higher

Refer to the Intel(R) Ethernet Adapters and Devices User Guide for currently
supported versions of these operating systems.


Safe Mode
=========
Safe Mode disables advanced and performance features, and supports only basic
traffic and minimal functionality, such as updating the NVM or downloading a
new driver or DDP package.

Refer to the Intel(R) Ethernet Adapters and Devices User Guide for more details
on DDP and Safe Mode.


Notes
=====
- In Linux, you cannot update the DDP package if any PF drivers are already
loaded. To overwrite a package, unload all PFs and then reload the driver with
the new package.

- In ESXi, use esxcli to load and unload DDP packages for specific market
segments during driver runtime.
 
- In Linux, only the first loaded PF per device can download a package for that
device. In ESXi, you can load different DDP packages for different PFs
associated with a device.

- If you are using DPDK, see the DPDK documentation at https://www.dpdk.org/
for installation instructions and more information.


Installation
============

Linux
-----
TO INSTALL THE OS DEFAULT DDP PACKAGE:

The Linux driver automatically installs the default DDP package file during
driver installation. Read the base driver README for general installation and
building instructions.

The DDP package loads during device initialization. The driver looks for
intel/ice/ddp/ice.pkg in your firmware root (typically /lib/firmware/ or
/lib/firmware/updates/) and checks that it contains a valid DDP package file.
The ice.pkg file is a symbolic link to the default DDP package file installed
by the linux-firmware software package or the out-of-tree driver installation.

TO INSTALL A DDP PACKAGE FOR SPECIFIC MARKET SEGMENTS:

You can install specific DDP package files for different physical devices in
the same system. To install a specific DDP package:

1. Download the DDP package file (ice_comms-x.x.x.x.zip) you want for your
device. In addition to licensing information and this README, this zip file
contains the following files:
    ice_comms-x.x.x.x.pkg
    ice.pkg

NOTE: The ice.pkg file is a Linux symbolic link file pointing to
ice_comms-x.x.x.x.pkg (in the same path).

2. Rename the ice_comms-x.x.x.x.pkg file as ice-xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx.pkg, where
'xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx' is the unique 64-bit PCI Express device serial number (in
hex) of the device you want the package downloaded on. The filename must
include the complete serial number (including leading zeros) and be all
lowercase. For example, if the 64-bit serial number is b887a3ffffca0568, then
the file name would be ice-b887a3ffffca0568.pkg.

To find the serial number from the PCI bus address, you can use the following
command:

# lspci -vv -s af:00.0 | grep -i Serial
Capabilities: [150 v1] Device Serial Number b8-87-a3-ff-ff-ca-05-68

You can use the following command to format the serial number without the
dashes:

# lspci -vv -s af:00.0 | grep -i Serial | awk '{print $7}' | sed s/-//g
b887a3ffffca0568

3. Copy the renamed DDP package file to /lib/firmware/updates/intel/ice/ddp/.
If the directory does not yet exist, create it before copying the file.

4. Unload all of the PFs on the device.

5. Reload the driver with the new package.

NOTE: The presence of a device-specific DDP package file overrides the loading
of the default DDP package file.


ESX
---
TO INSTALL THE OS DEFAULT DDP PACKAGE:

The default DDP package is installed as part of the driver binary. You don't
need to take additional steps to install the DDP package file.

TO INSTALL A DDP PACKAGE FOR SPECIFIC MARKET SEGMENTS:

You must first install the Intel(R) ESXCLI Plug-In for Managing Intel(R)
Ethernet Network Adapters to be able to install and load market-specific DDP
packages. Download it from:
https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/download/19380/intel-esxcli-plug-in-for-
managing-intel-ethernet-network-adapters.html

NOTE: ESXi support for DDP packages for specific market segments requires the
following:
- OS: ESXi 6.7 or higher
- Driver: icen 1.9.1.x or higher
- Tool: intnet 1.8.3.x or higher

To install and load this DDP package:

1. Download and install the esxcli plug-in from the URL above.

2. Download the DDP package.

3. Copy the DDP package file to the following location: /store/intel/icen/ddp/.
   If the directory does not yet exist, create it before copying the file.

4. From the command prompt, run the following command to load the DDP package:

   # esxcli intnet ddp load -n <vmnicX> -p <ddp_file_name> -f

   Where:
    <vmnicX> = the name of the NIC
    <ddp_file_name> = the name of the DDP package to load
    -f = forces the package to load

    NOTE: This operation will cause the driver to reset.

5. Wait for the load result status.


To list all active DDP packages for all virtual NICs, run the following:

# esxcli intnet ddp list

To unload (roll back) a DDP package, run the following:

# esxcli intnet ddp rollback -n <vmnicX> -f

NOTE: This operation will cause the driver to reset.


Troubleshooting
===============

Linux
-----
If you encounter issues with the DDP package file, you may need to download an
updated driver or DDP package file. Refer to the log messages for more
information.

ESX
---
If you encounter issues with the DDP package file, download the latest driver.


Legal / Disclaimers
===================
Copyright (c) 2019 - 2022, Intel Corporation.

Intel and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation or its
subsidiaries in the U.S. and/or other countries.

*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others.

This software and the related documents are Intel copyrighted materials, and
your use of them is governed by the express license under which they were
provided to you ("License"). Unless the License provides otherwise, you may not
use, modify, copy, publish, distribute, disclose or transmit this software or
the related documents without Intel's prior written permission.
This software and the related documents are provided as is, with no express or
implied warranties, other than those that are expressly stated in the License.
